McKelvey, Jean T. Additional Files /4202
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation & Archives
Jean T. McKelvey Additional Files
1954-1995
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation & Archives
McKelvey, Jean T.
/4202
1 cubic feet
1 linear ft.
Records (documents).
8051247
General
Contact Information:
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation and Archives Martin P. Catherwood Library 227 Ives Hall Cornell University Ithaca, NY 14853 (607) 255-3183> kheel_center@cornell.edu http://www.ilr.cornell.edu/library/kheel-center
Compiled by:
Kheel Staff, July 28, 2014
EAD encoding:
Randall Miles, October 04, 2016
Biographical / Historical
Jean McKelvey (February 9, 1908 January 5, 1998) was one of the founding faculty at the New York State School of Industrial and Labor Relations at Cornell University in 1946, the first female member of the National Academy of Arbitrators (NAA) in 1947, the NAA's first female president in 1970, and an accomplished author of many works on arbitration and other labor topics. The first fully endowed chair at the ILR School was named the Jean McKelvey-Alice Grant Professorship of Labor-Management Relations.
A graduate of Wellesley College (AB '29, MA '31) and Radcliffe College (PhD '33), McKelvey taught at Sarah Lawrence College from 1932 to 1945. She joined the newly-formed New York State School of Industrial and Labor Relations in 1946 as the school's first professor, reaching the rank of full professor in 1951. She became Professor Emerita in 1976. In addition to developing the ILR School's fields of study with Maurice Neufeld, teaching at the ILR School, and conducting scholarly research, McKelvey served on the Region II National War Labor Board (1944-1945), New York State Board of Mediation (1955-1966), the Federal Services Impasses Panel (1979-1990), and other boards and panels.
Among her many honors and awards were the Federal Mediation and Conciliation Service's Special Award for Distinguished Service in Labor Management Relations (1973), Arbitrator of the Year Award from the American Arbitration Association (1983), and Distinguished Services Awards from Wellesley College (1975), the Society of Professionals in Dispute Resolution (1989), and the Society of Federal Labor Relations Professionals (1990).
See the Cornell University Faculty Memorial Statement for Professor Jean McKelvey: http://hdl.handle.net/1813/18133
Conditions Governing Access
Access to the collections in the Kheel Center is restricted. Please contact a reference archivist for access to these materials.
Related Materials
Related Collections: /3001: Jean T. McKelvey Papers /4165 OHT: Jean T. McKelvey Interview with Ronald Schatz /4208: Maurice F. Neufeld and Jean T. McKelvey, eds. "Industrial Relations at the Dawn of the New Millennium" Monograph 5154: New York City Office of Collective Bargaining Records
McKelvey, Jean T.(Jean Trepp), 1908-1998; New York State School of Industrial and Labor Relations
8051247
- Arbitration, 1991 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Seminar - Arbitration, 1983-1991 (Box 1, Folder 2)
- ILR 602 - Arbitration (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Newspaper Clippings, 1941-1947 (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Retirement Form, 1968-1985 (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Correspondence, 1940-1953 (Box 1, Folder 6)
- Labor Arbitration, 1984-1988 (Box 1, Folder 7)
- Opinion and Awards, 1970-1982 (Box 1, Folder 8)
- Landmark Decisions on Labor Arbitration (Box 1, Folder 9)
- Daily Labor Report, 1965-1979 (Box 1, Folder 10)
- Arbitrations, 1954-1994 (Box 1, Folder 11)
- Labor Arbitration Proceedings Grievance No. 123, 1987 (Box 1, Folder 12)
- Study Time, 1987-1995 (Box 1, Folder 13)
- Jean McKelvey - Killingsworth, 1987 (Box 1, Folder 14)
- United States Court of Appeals, 1971-1985 (Box 1, Folder 15)
- Brown Co. - IAM, 1971-1987 (Box 1, Folder 16)
- Public Review Board International Union, UAW, 1982-1989 (Box 1, Folder 17)
- Continuing Education Conference Background Materials, 1987 (Box 1, Folder 18)
- Continuing Education Conference Discussion Cases, 1987 (Box 1, Folder 19)
- Paul Alfred Salvatore Senior Thesis, 1981 (Box 1, Folder 20)